<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Pankaj Kumar (Posts about coronavirus)</title><link>https://pankajkarman.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://pankajkarman.github.io/categories/coronavirus.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:pankaj.kmr1990@gmail.com"&gt;Pankaj Kumar&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Jul 2020 21:18:15 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Coronavirus: A comprehensive review of mode of transmission </title><link>https://pankajkarman.github.io/blog/covid/</link><dc:creator>Pankaj Kumar</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This blog reviews a &lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0925753520302630?via%3Dihub"&gt;journal article&lt;/a&gt; published in June 2020; investigating the airborne transmission of COVID19.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the severity of the disease and healthcare facilities in our country, &lt;a href="https://www.wired.com/story/to-beat-covid-19-you-have-to-know-how-a-virus-moves/?fbclid=IwAR1IX3J2iWA_2zNL_ZrRjFg3vtHEBO1JW-UGlKm1_dPHwm8uafcJYdNDCsk"&gt;it is very important and imperative to understand the causes of the infection and ways to avoid it&lt;/a&gt;. While it is a novel disease and there is still a lot of research going on, there is a more or less a consensus amongs scientists about the mode of transmission of the virus. It was thought to be spreading through droplets in the beginning but now a lot of evidences are coming in the public domain regarding the possible aerosol transmission mode. Here in this blog, I'll be discussing about a few papers which have convincingly demonstarted the dominance of aerosol transmission for the spread of the virus. At the end, I'll discus about the scientific reasoning about the steps being recommended to avoid contracting the virus and the role of ventilation in avoiding the spread of the virus. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Symptoms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://reader.elsevier.com/reader/sd/pii/S0195670120302590?token=73EE9C07DD326FE2DE5CE1B6871673C690D1CA0E8FE0DF4226322A7BE6D8981C794CA5CC351B2395AFEE69739019B906"&gt;The most common symptoms are fever, fatigue, muscle pain, and dry cough&lt;/a&gt;. Some patients may exhibit nasal congestion, chills, sore throat or diarrhoea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fever (74% covid +ve vs 22% covid -ve)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cough&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.health.com/condition/infectious-diseases/coronavirus/what-does-shortness-of-breath-feel-like"&gt;Dyspnea (shortness of breath)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.healthline.com/health/sore-throat#symptoms"&gt;Sore throat&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://edition.cnn.com/2020/04/03/health/smell-taste-test-coronavirus-wellness/index.html"&gt;Loss of taste or smell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the aforementioned study, Approximately 17% covid +ve did not report fever, cough, shortness of breath, or sore throat. Among them, &lt;a href="https://www.healthline.com/health/chills"&gt;chills&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.verywellhealth.com/myalgia-overview-4584594"&gt;muscle pain or myalgia&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhinitis"&gt;stuffy nose or coryza&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://www.healthline.com/health/malaise"&gt;malaise&lt;/a&gt; were the most common symptoms. Symptoms are mild in about 80%, moderate to severe in 15% and critical in 5% of cases. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7zzfdYShvQU&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be"&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="https://img.youtube.com/vi/7zzfdYShvQU/0.jpg" width='650"' height="400"&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Modes of transmission&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although data on factors related to this transmission are scarce, the spread of SARS-CoV-2 is thought to be mostly via the transmission of respiratory droplets coming from infected individuals and fomite transmission (transmission via infected surfaces). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0013935120307143-gr2_lrg.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Small droplets, from submicron to approximately 10 μm diameter, produced during speech and coughing, have been shown to contain viral particles, which can remain viable and infectious in aerosols for 3 h. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The droplets can be transmitted either directly by entering the airway through the air (aerosols), or indirectly by contact transfer via contaminated hands (fomite transmission). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fomite transmission may happen via infected surfaces like doorknobs, elevator buttons, handrails, phones, switches, pens, keyboards and even via stethoscope if not disinfected before use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mode of transmission could affect whether an infection starts in the upper or lower respiratory tract, which is thought to affect the severity of the disease progression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, Human-to-human transmission of COVID-19 occurs primarily via three routes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Large droplets that are expelled with sufficient momentum so as to directly impact the recipients’ mouth, nose or conjunctiva (Droplet transmission).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/ina.12682"&gt;Physical contact with droplets deposited on a surface and subsequent transfer to the recipient’s respiratory mucosa (Fomite transmission)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inhalation by the recipient of aerosolized droplet nuclei from the expiratory ejecta that are
delivered by ambient air currents (Airborne transmission)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/video/scientists-say-coronavirus-can-be-spread-farther-than-6-feet-in-tiny-airborne-particles/#x"&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="https://www.thailandmedical.news/uploads/editor/files/Coronavirus-Airborne.jpg" width='650"' height="400"&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each stage in the transmission process is mediated by complex flow phenomena, ranging from air–mucous interaction, liquid sheet fragmentation, turbulent jets, and droplet evaporation and deposition, to flow-induced particle dispersion and sedimentation. Thus, flow physics is central to the transmission of COVID-19. Furthermore, given the importance of flow phenomena to the transmission process, the methods, devices and practices employed to mitigate respiratory infections are also rooted in the principles of fluid dynamics. These include simple methods such as hand washing and wearing face masks, to fogging machines, ventilation and even practices such as social distancing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Damages caused by COVID19&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are evidences emerging that COVID causes damages to &lt;a href="https://www.medicalnewstoday.com/articles/covid-19-doctors-round-up-evidence-of-damage-outside-the-lungs#Direct-damage-to-tissues"&gt;multiple organs&lt;/a&gt; like kidneys, liver, heart, brain and nervous system, skin and gastrointestinal tract instead of just lungs as was thought in the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Patients have suffered from strokes and neurological disorders, including inflammation, psychosis and delirium, and these may persist for many months even after recovering from the disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/pulmonary-fibrosis/symptoms-causes/syc-20353690"&gt;Lung fibrosis (scarring of lung tissues)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.webmd.com/lung/what-is-a-pulmonary-embolism"&gt;Pulmonary Embolism (blood clots in the pulmonary artery)&lt;/a&gt; have been observed in people long after they have recovered from the disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Patients with severe symptoms may require oxygen support at home even months after their recoveries. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/video/coronavirus-understanding-damage-covid-19-does-to-body/#x"&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="https://i.ytimg.com/vi/soNC8nhk6Yc/maxresdefault.jpg" width='650"' height="400"&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ways to avoid the transmission&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For detailed discussion about the measures to mitigate the spread of virus, please have a look at &lt;a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/journal-of-fluid-mechanics/article/flow-physics-of-covid19/476E32549012B3620D2452F30F2567F1"&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hand Washing:&lt;/strong&gt; Due to polar hydrophilic and non-polar hydrophobic sides, soap molecules can easily attach to oils and lipids emulsifying the content in the process which is then washed away with water. Moreover, soap molecules also deactivate the virus by dismantling its lipid envelope. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3SfHdSHK-g0"&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="https://img.youtube.com/vi/3SfHdSHK-g0/0.jpg" width='650"' height="400"&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Face masks:&lt;/strong&gt; Face masks provide ‘inward’ protection by filtering virus-laden aerosolized particles that would otherwise be inhaled by an uninfected person, and ‘outward’ protection by trapping virus-laden droplets expelled by an infected person. The effectiveness of a simple face mask such as the surgical, N95 or homemade cloth face mask is a function of the combined effect of the filtering properties of the face-mask material, the fit of the mask on the face and the related leaks from the perimeter of the face mask.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;a. Inward protection&lt;/em&gt;: The face-mask material traps droplets and particles via the combined effects of diffusion, inertial impaction, interception and electrostatic attraction. The process of inhalation generates a low pressure in the region interior to the face mask, thereby sealing (or at least reducing) perimeter leaks. Thus, with a reasonably well-fitted face mask, inward protection depends primarily on the face-mask filter material. Studies have shown that, for a given filter, there is an intermediate particle size where filtration efficiency is minimum. Below this size, electrostatic attraction (active for masks such as N95) and diffusion dominate filtration, whereas above this size, impaction and interception are the dominant mechanisms. An increase in fibre density to enhance filtration efficiency is accompanied by an increased pressure drop across the mask (Lai, Poon &amp;amp; Cheung 2012), which requires a greater inhalation effort by the wearer. Thus, an appropriate balance has to be achieved via proper design of the filter material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;b. Outward protection&lt;/em&gt; : The outward protection afforded by face masks has emerged as a particularly important issue in the COVID-19 pandemic because a SARS-CoV-2 transmission may occur early in the course of infection, not only from symptomatic patients but also from asymptomatic as well as minimally symptomatic patients. While a mask can significantly reduce the velocity of the throughflow jet during expiratory events, the increased pressure in the region between the mask and the face pushes the face mask outwards, resulting in increased perimeter leakage. The leakage jets that issue from the perimeter can be turbulent and highly directed. Spasmodic expiratory events such as coughing and sneezing that generate high transient expulsion velocities will significantly diminish the outward protection effectiveness of face masks. Please have a look at &lt;a href="https://academic.oup.com/annweh/article/57/4/493/158021"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-018-35693-w"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; for detailed CFD simulations of flow through N95 masks and factors affecting their efficiencies. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4xFY3aPF7E4"&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="https://img.youtube.com/vi/4xFY3aPF7E4/0.jpg" width='650"' height="400"&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0021850220300744?via%3Dihub"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social Distancing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.thelancet.com/pdfs/journals/lanres/PIIS2213-2600(20)30245-9.pdf"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proper ventilation of indoor environment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/video/experts-suggest-improving-ventilation-may-reduce-coronavirus-spread/"&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="https://external-content.duckduckgo.com/iu/?u=https%3A%2F%2Ftse4.mm.bing.net%2Fth%3Fid%3DOIP.R3952kFl90e32XzHH5V6cwHaD4%26pid%3DApi&amp;amp;f=1" width='650"' height="400"&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fogging: &lt;/strong&gt; Fogging machines, relying on the dispersion of a fine mist of disinfectants in the air,  provide an effective means for disinfecting large spaces, such as hospitals, and grocery stores. Fogging machines are designed based on the flow physics of aerosolization, with their droplet size is below 10 μm facilitating extended airborne duration. 
Considering their droplet size range, they rely on the collision between aerosol droplets of disinfectent generated during fogging and droplets holding viruses supported mainly by the diffusion process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S014139102030183X"&gt;Decontamination of face masks to extend its uses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.wired.com/story/to-beat-covid-19-you-have-to-know-how-a-virus-moves/?fbclid=IwAR1IX3J2iWA_2zNL_ZrRjFg3vtHEBO1JW-UGlKm1_dPHwm8uafcJYdNDCsk"&gt;To Beat Covid-19, You Have to Know How A Virus Moves&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0013935120307143"&gt;Transmission of COVID-19 virus by droplets and aerosols: A critical review on the unresolved dichotomy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.pnas.org/content/117/26/14857"&gt;Identifying airborne transmission as the dominant route for the spread of COVID-19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://indianexpress.com/article/explained/what-we-know-of-coronavirus-covid-19-symptoms-cure-treatment-6513460/"&gt;What we know of Covid-19 now: Updated symptoms, modes of transmission, immunity and complications&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.webmd.com/lung/news/20200423/the-great-invader-how-covid-attacks-every-organ"&gt;The Great Invader: How COVID Attacks Every Organ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.medicalnewstoday.com/articles/covid-19-doctors-round-up-evidence-of-damage-outside-the-lungs"&gt;COVID-19: Doctors round up evidence of damage outside the lungs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/video/coronavirus-understanding-damage-covid-19-does-to-body/#x"&gt;Understanding the extent of damage COVID-19 does to the body&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S014139102030183X"&gt;Extended use of face masks during the COVID-19 pandemic - Thermal conditioning and spray-on surface disinfection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>coronavirus</category><category>covid</category><guid>https://pankajkarman.github.io/blog/covid/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 01:16:34 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>